<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>TCPMon Tutorial</title>
    </properties>
<body>
<section name="Content">
<macro name="toc"/>
</section>
<section name="Introduction">

<p>TCPMon is a utility that allows the user to monitor the messages passed
along in TCP based conversation. It is based on a swing UI and works on
almost all platforms that Java supports. The aim of this simple tutorial is
to explain how TCPMon works and also to explain some of its features.</p>
</section>
<section name="Structure and Dependencies">

<p>TCPMon has absolutely no dependencies on third party libraries. But some
of the UI features rely on JDK 1.4 so TCPMon needs a JRE that is 1.4 or
higher.</p>
</section>
<section name="Usage Patterns">
<subsection name="As an Explicit Intermediate">

<p>The most common usage pattern for the TCPMon is as an
<strong>intermediary</strong>. It is called <strong>explicit</strong> since
the client has to point to the intermediary rather than the original endpoint
in order to monitor the messages. The following figure explains this
concept.</p>

<p><img alt="concept" src="images/concept.jpg"/></p>

<p>In order to start the TCPMon in this configuration one has to provide the
host name and the port for the listener in the admin screen. See image
below.</p>

<p><img alt="first screen" src="images/screen1.jpg"/></p>

<p>Pressing the 'add' button opens up a new tab that allows the messages to
be seen as in the following screen</p>

<p><img alt="message screen" src="images/screen2.jpg"/></p>

<p>At this point the requester should point to the listener port of the
TCPMon instead of the original endpoint. Let us understand this with an
example:</p>

<p>Say all messages passed between www.apache.org needs to be monitored.</p>

<p><strong>Step 1</strong> - Add a listener with host as www.apache.org and
port as 80. Set the listener to port 8080 which may be any unused port in the
local machine</p>

<p><img alt="the settings" src="images/screen2-closeup2.jpg"/></p>

<p><strong>Step 2</strong> - Point the browser to localhost:8080 instead of
www.apache.org.</p>

<p><img alt="browser address bar" src="images/screen2-browser.jpg"/></p>

<p>Once the messages start flowing they can be seen in the relevant tab as
seen below.</p>

<p><img alt="Filles screen" src="images/screen3.jpg"/></p>

<p>The bottom controls allow the messages to be XML formatted (useful in
debugging Web services), save and resend the messages, and also to switch the
layout of the message windows.</p>

<p><img alt="button set" src="images/screen2-closeup1.jpg"/></p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="As a Request Sender for Web Services">

<p>TCPMon can also be used as a request sender for Web services. The request
SOAP message can be pasted on the send screen and then sent directly to the
server.</p>

<p><img alt="request sender" src="images/screen4.jpg"/></p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="As a Proxy">

<p>TCPMon can act as a proxy. To start the TCPMon at proxy mode, just select
the proxy option from the radio buttons. When acting as a proxy, TCPMon only
needs the listener port to be configured.</p>

<p><img alt="proxy" src="images/screen5.jpg"/></p>
</subsection>
</section>
<section name="Advanced Settings">
<subsection name="Slow Connection Simulation">

<p>TCPMon can simulate a slow connection, in which case the delay and the
bytes to be dropped can be configured. This is specially useful in testing
Web services.</p>

<p><img alt="slow-connection" src="images/screen6.jpg"/></p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="HTTP Proxy support">

<p>If HTTP proxy support is required then that can also be set on the admin
screen.</p>
</subsection>
</section>
<section name="Conclusion">

<p>TCPMon is a simple and easy to use tool that has many benefits when
developing message driven applications. It is particularly useful in
developing Web services</p>
</section>
</body>
</document>
